本节我们研究ElGamal公钥加密系统的安全性
In this segment, we're gonna study the
security of the ElGamal public key
我提醒一下大家，当我们第一次展示
encryption system. So let me remind you
that when we first presented the
Diffie-Hellman协议的时候，我们说过，其安全性是基于假设的
Diffie-Hellman protocol, we said that the
security is based on the assumption that
即给定g, g^a和g^b，很难计算出
says that given G, G to the A, G to the B,
it's difficult to compute the
Diffie-Hellman密钥g^ab的。这是攻击者所必须做的
Diffie-Hellman secret, G to the AB. This
is basically what the attacker has to do.
他看到Alice的贡献，和Bob的贡献，他的目标是
He sees Alice's contribution. He sees
Bob's contribution and then his goal is to
解出Diffie-Hellman密钥。我们说过这个问题是困难的
figure out what the Diffie-Hellman secret
is. And we said that this problem is
这个论断，即这个问题是困难的
difficult. The statement that the problem
is difficult is what's called the
就是所谓的计算Diffie-Hellman假设。
那么我们更为准确地看这个假设
computational Diffie-Hellman assumption.
So, let's take this assumption more
那么通常我们看一个n阶有限循环群
precisely. So, as usual we're going to
look at a finite cyclic group of order N,
那么G是某个群，大家应把它想成Z_p^*
so G is some group, in your head you should be
thinking ZP star, but there could
但是也可以是其他群，例如椭圆曲线群。如果我们说
be other groups, for example, like an ellipctic curve group. And then we say that
计算Diffie-Hellman假设，我用简写
the computational Diffie-Hellman
assumption. I've often used the shorthand
CDH来表示计算Diffie-Hellman假设。
我们说这个假设在G上成立
CDH for Computational Diffie Hellman.
We'll say this assumption holds in G if
如果如下条件成立，即对任意有效算法
the following condition holds, namely for
all efficient algorithms. If we choose a
如果我们选择一个随机生成元，那么我们随机选择
Z_N中的指数a和b
random generator, and then we choose
random exponents A, B in ZN. Then when
那么我们把g,g^a,g^b给算法
we give the algorithm G, G to the A, and G
to the B, the probability that the
算法会产生出正确的Diffie-Hellman密钥的
概率是可忽略的。如果这对所有
algorithm will produce the Diffie Hellman
secret is negligible. If this is true for
有效算法都成立，那么我们说CDH假设在G上成立
all efficient algorithms, then we say that
the CDH assumption holds for G. CDH, as I
我说过CDH代表计算Diffie-Hellman假设。实际上，这个假设
said, stands for Computational Diffie
Hellman. As it turns out, this assumption
对于分析ElGamal系统的安全性并不理想
is not ideal for analyzing the security of
the ElGamal system. And instead I'm gonna
我要接着引入一个稍微更强一点的假设，叫做哈希
go ahead and make a slightly stronger
assumption called a hash Diffie-Hellman
Diffie-Hellman假设，好，那什么是哈希Diffie-Hellman假设？
assumption. Okay. So what is hash
Diffie-Hellman assumption? Again, we are
我们还是关注一个特定群G，现在我们引入一个哈希函数H
focusing on a particular group G and now
we're also gonna introduce a hash function
它把许多G中的元素对映射到某个对称加密系统的密钥空间里
H that maps pairs of elements in G into
the key space of some symmetric encryption
然后我们说这是哈希Diffie-Hellman假设
system. And then we say that the hash
Diffie-Hellman assumption, or HDH for
或简记为HDH，对于二元组(G,H)成立，G是群，H是哈希函数
short, holds for this pair, G comma H for
the group in the hash function if the
如果如下条件满足。如果我选择一个随机生成元
following is true. Basically, if I choose
a random generator and then I choose
然后我随机选择Z_N中的指数a和b，那么我也
随机选择一对r和k
random exponents A and B in ZN and then I
also choose a random R and K, then the
那么下面的两个分布是不可区分的
following distributions are
computationally indistinguishable. That
即，如果我给你g, g^a, g^b，那么这个哈希值
is, if I give you G, G to the A, G to the
B, and then this hash value, this should
大家应用对它挺熟。这个哈希值在ElGamal系统中
look familiar to you. This is the hash
value that's used in the ElGamal system to
被用来推出对称加密的密钥。我们说这个分布
derive the symmetric encryption key. What
we're saying is that this distribution is
与另一个分布不可区分。在另一个分布中，
同样是给定g, g^a, g^b
indistinguishable from a distribution
where you're also given. G, G to the A, G
但现在，不给哈希值，你只有随机的密钥
to the B. But now, instead of giving the
hash, you're given just really random key.
那么这个假设是说，在ElGamal系统中，对称加密时
So what this assumption says is that the
symmetric key that was derived during
推出的密钥，本质上与一个
encryption in the ElGamal system,
essentially is indistinguishable from a
真随机密钥不可区分，这个真随机密钥是根据
truly random key that is derived
independently from the rest of the
系统中余下的参数推出的，是一个独立的真随机密钥
parameters of the system. It's a truly
independent random key, looks basically
看起来和我们使用的密钥几乎一样。我们使用的密钥
是根据g^a和g^b推出的
the same as the key that we used, to
derive from the G to the A and the G to
现在我想指出，这个哈希Diffie-Hellman假设
the B. Now I'd like to point out that the
Hash Diffie-Hellman assumption is actually
实际上比计算Diffie-Hellman假设要强
a stronger assumption than the
Computational Diffie-Hellman assumption.
证明的方法是看逆否命题
The way to see that is using the contra
positive, that is suppose the
即假设计算Diffie-Hellman假设在群G上容易解决
Computational Diffie-Hellman assumption
happens to be easy in the group G. Then I
那么我宣布，哈希Diffie-Hellman假设也是容易解决的
claim that in fact the Hash Diffie-Hellman
assumption is also easy in the group G. In
事实上，我说对于g和h，这是成立的，事实上，
对于所有的哈希函数
fact, I'll say for G, H and this is true
in fact for all hash functions where the
若哈希函数的像至少含有两个元素。换句话说
image of the hash function. It contains at
least two elements. In other words all I
哈希Diffie-Hellman假设是容易的
want to say is that the Hash Diffie-Hellman assumption and it's easy for all
如果所有的哈希函数把一切都映射到一个点。
这对于我们感兴趣的
hash functions to go match everything to a
single point. Which is true for almost all
所有哈希函数都成立。那么这是一个很简单的
hash functions of interest to us. So
actually, this is a really simple
命题，我们来证明它。如果计算Diffie-Hellman假设是容易的
statement to prove. Basically, if the
Computational Diffie-Hellman assumption is easy, what that
这意味着，有了g^a, g^b，我可以计算g^ab
says is that, given G to the A and G to the B, I can actually calculate G to the AB
因为我知道哈希函数H，我完全可以计算这里的值
myself. Cuz I know the hash function H, I
can calculate this complete value here. So
那么如果你给我一组左边的样本，或是右边的样本
if you give me a tuple that's
sampled from the left or sampled from the
我都可以轻松地分辨其来源。如果它取自左边
right. I can very easily tell where it's
from. If it's sampled from the left, then
那么我一旦自己计算g^ab，我就可以测试组里的最后一个元素
once I've calculated G to the AB myself, I
can just test that the last element in the
是否就是g^b和g^ab的哈希值。如果是，我就知道了
tuple is, in fact, the hash of G to
the B and G to the AB. If it is, I know
这个样本是取自左边的；如果不是，我就知道是取自右边的
the sample is from the left. If it isn't,
I know the sample is from the right. Okay,
那么这给了我很高的优势来区分这两个分布
so this gives me pretty high advantage, in
distinguishing these two distributions. So
所以CDH容易的话，非常容易就能看出这些分布是可区分的
CDH is easy, it's very easy to see that
these distributions are distinguishable.
这就是说，如果哈希Diffie-Hellman实际上很难解决
And this basically says that if the Hash
Diffie-Hellman is in fact hard, then CDH
那么CDH也将是很难的，那么我们说，
因此哈希Diffie-Hellman假设
must also be hard. Which then we say, that
therefore the Hash Diffie-Hellman is a
是一个更强的假设。可能会有CDH困难的集合，但HDH不困难
stronger assumption. There might be group
where CDH is hard, but HDH is not hard.
那么我们说HDH是一个更强的假设
Okay. So we say HDH is a
stronger assumption. If you found this
如果你觉得这种强弱假设的讨论难以理解
discussion of weak assumption versus
strong assumption confusing, it's not
这点其实并不重要，可以忽略。重要的是
really that important, it's fine to ignore
it. The important thing that I want to
我想给大家展示，事实上哈希Diffie-Hellman假设
show you is in fact that the Hash
Diffie-Hellman assumption is sufficient to
足以证明ElGamal系统的语义安全了。在证明之前
prove the semantic security of the ElGamal
system. Before we do that let me quickly
我简单问一下大家下面的问题，以确保哈希Diffie-Hellman
假设已经弄清楚了
ask you the following puzzle just to make
sure the Hash Diffie-Hellman assumption is
设想我们的密钥空间是｛0, 1｝^128，即128位字符串
clear. So imagine our key space is ｛0, 1｝ to the 128. So 128 bit strings and our
我们的哈希函数把一对群元素映射成128位字符串
hash function will map pairs of group
elements into this 128 byte strings.
假设我们选择一个哈希函数满足
Suppose it so happens that we chose a hash
function such that it always outputs
他的输出总是以0开始。换句话说，输出的128位字符串的
strings that begin with zero. In other
words, of the 128 bit strings the most
最高位总是0。如果我们选择一个哈希函数
significant bit of the output is always
zero. If we chose such a hash function,
那么哈希Diffie-Hellman假设对(G,H)还成立吗？
does the Hash Diffie-Hellman assumption
hold for this pair, G comma H. So the
答案是否定的，它不成立。原因是因为现在
answer is no it doesn't hold. And the
reason is because it now very easy to
容易区分这两个分布，左边和右边的分布
distinguish the two distributions that we
have here. The distribution on the left
区分两者的方法是
an the distribution on the right. And the
way you would distinguish the two is
如果我随机选择K=｛0, 1｝^128中的元素
basically if I choose a truly random
element in K, in ｛0, 1｝ to the 128,
那么最高位是0的概率是1/2。不过
then mostly it can very well be zero with
probability one half. However, the tuple
当给我的样本是选自左边分布时，哈希值的最高位
that's given to me is chosen from the left
distribution, then the most significant
总是0，因此如果我看到0，我就说
bit of the hash will always be zero and
therefore if I see zero, I'm gonna say the
分布是来自左边的。如果我看到1，就说
distribution is a distribution on the
left. If I see one, I'm gonna say the
是来自右边的分布。这会给我1/2的优势
distribution is a distribution on the
right. That will give me advantage one
以区分这两个分布。因此
half in distinguishing these two
distributions. And so as a result, the
哈希Diffie-Hellman假设在这里不成立。那么大家清楚地看到
Hash Diffie-Hillman assumption is false in
this case. So clearly you could see that,
即使CDH可能在群G上是困难的，如果你选择了
even though CDH might be hard in a certain
group G, if you choose a bad hash
一个不好的哈希函数，那么HDH在这个(G,H)上也不成立
function, then HDH will not hold for the
pair G comma H. Okay. But suppose it so
假设我们选择了一个群G和一个哈希函数H
happens that we choose a group G and a
hash function H for which the Hash Diffie
使得哈希Diffie-Hellman假设成立。事实上，
如果你选择的哈希函数
Hellman assumption holds. And in fact, if
you choose the hash function to be just
是SHA-256，我们知道哈希Diffie-Hellman假设
SHA-256, for all we know, the Hash
Diffie Hellman assumption holds in the
在群Z_p^*上成立，在椭圆曲线群上成立。
我的目标是给大家证明
group ZP star, and holds in elliptic curve
groups. My goal then is to show you that
ElGamal在哈希Diffie-Hellman假设下是语义安全的
ElGamal is semantically secure under
the Hash Diffie-Hellman assumption. So let me
我来提醒大家ElGamal系统是如何工作的
quickly remind you how the ElGamal
system works. While we're gonna choose a
我们选择一个随机生成元g，随机选择Z_N中的一个a
random generator G, we're gonna choose a
random 'a' in ZN, the public key is
公钥就是(g, g^a)，私钥就是a。现在
gonna be G, and G to the A, the secret key
is simply gonna be A. And now here I wrote
我这里简写了ElGamal加密。要加密时
shorthand for the ElGamal encryption.
Basically, what to encrypt, what we do is
我们选择一个随机数b，计算(g^b,h^b)的哈希值
we choose a random B. We hash G as being H
to the B. Remember this H to the B is the
这个h^b就是g^ab，是Diffie-Hellman密钥。这个哈希函数
value G to the AB. This is the Diffie
Hellman secret. The hash function gave us
给我们一个对称加密密钥k。我们使用k加密明文信息
a symmetric encryption key K. We encrypt
the message with K, and we output G to the
输出g^b与对称加密的密文。解密时，我们取值u
B and the symmetric cipher text. To
decrypt we hash the value U, and the Diffie
和Diffie-Hellman密钥，g^a的哈希值。
这就推出了一个对称密钥，我们可以来解密密文了
Hellman secret, G to the A. To derive a
symmetric key, we decrypt the cipher text.
然后我们输出明文m。那么我们来看如何证明
And then we output the plaintext message m. So let's see how to argue that,
事实上，ElGamal在哈希Diffie-Hellman假设下是语义安全的
in fact, ElGamal is semantically secure under
this Hash Diffie-Hillman assumption is
证明很简单。我们必须证明，在语义安全里
fairly simple. So well we have to argue,
remember we had, in semantic security, we
我们有这两个实验。在一个实验中，攻击者有
have these two experiments. One
experiment, the attacker is given the
m0的加密结果；在另一个实验中，攻击者有m1的加密结果
encryption of m0. In the other experiment,
the attacker is given the encryption of m1.
那么我在这里写了两个实验。大家注意挑战者开始时
So I wrote the two experiments here. Here
you notice that the attacker starts by
(口误：attacker->challenger)
把公钥发送给攻击者。然后攻击者选择两个
sending off the public key to the
adversary. The adversary then chooses two
等长度的信息m0和m1。然后如果他获得了m0的ElGamal加密
equal length messages m0 and m1. And then
if he gets the ElGamal encryption of M0,
以及一段ElGamal密文。类似地
and a kind of rough shorthand for what
ElGamal ciphertext is, okay? Similarly, in
在实验1中，他会得到m1的加密，而非m0的
encryption one, he simply gets the
encryption of M1 instead of M0, and
两个实验的其余部分是一样的。现在
everything else is the same about these
two experiments. Now, because of the Hash
因为哈希Diffie-Hellman假设，即使攻击者看到
Diffie-Hellman assumption, we know that
even though the attacker got to see G, G
g, g^a, g^b，我们知道(g^b, g^ab)的哈希输出
to the a and G to the b, we know that the
output of the hash of G to the b, G to the
与随机数是无法区分的。因此如果我们
ab is indistinguishable from random.
Therefore, if we replace the actual hash
用真随机、完全独立的密钥k来替换这哈希函数结果
function by a truly generated random key K
that's independent of everything else, by
根据哈希Diffie-Hellman假设，攻击者无法区分这两个游戏
the Hash Diffie-Hellman assumption, the
attacker can't distinguish these two
这对于大家是一个简单的练习，试证
games. And again, it's a simple exercise
for you to show that if he could
如果攻击者可以区分这两个游戏，
那么他就违反了哈希Diffie-Hellman假设
distinguish these two games, then he would
break the Hash Diffie-Hellman assumption.
然后对实验1也是一样。攻击者也无法区分
But then the same is true for experiment
one. The attacker also could not
哈希函数值和真随机密钥
distinguish the output of the hash
function from a truly random key, that was
用来生成挑战密文。好，那么现在我们看
used the generate the challenge cipher
text. Okay. So now basically we look at
这两个使用，我们发现，等一下。。
these two experiments and we realize that,
wait a minute, what's going on in these
这两个实验发生了什么？基本上是一样的，除了在一个实验中
two experiments? Basically everything is
the same except in one experiment, the
攻击者获得的是m0的对称加密系统加密后的密文
attacker gets the encryption under
a symmetric encryption system of m0. In the
另一个实验中，攻击者获得了m1的对称加密
other one, he gets the encryption under a
symmetric encryption system of m1 and the
密钥是随机独立地选择的。那么根据
key is chosen at random independently over
everything else. So by the fact that the
对称加密系统是语义安全这一事实
symmetric encryption system is
semantically secure, these two games are
这两个游戏是不可区分的。如果它们可以被区分
indistinguishable. If they were
distinguishable, then the attacker could
那么攻击者可以破解这个对称加密系统的语义安全
break the semantic security of this
symmetric encryption system. So now we
那么现在我们证明这个等价关系的链
kinda prove this, you know, this chain of
equivalences. And that proves that the
这证明了最初的游戏事实上是不可区分的
original games, in fact, are
indistinguishable, computationally
计算上不可区分的。因此。ElGamal系统是语义安全的
indistinguishable. And therefore, the
ElGamal system is semantically secure.
好，这像是我用图像进行的简单证明
Okay so it's like I said a very simple
proof by pictures and you can make this
大家可以不费力就把这个写成严格的证明。
不过，语义安全是不够的
into a rigorous proof without too much
work. But semantic security isn't enough,
我们真正想要的是选择密文安全，问题是
what we really want is chosen ciphertext
security, and the question is ElGamal chosen ciphertext
ElGamal是选择密文安全的吗？实际上，
为了证明ElGamal是选择密文安全的
secure? So it turns out to prove the
chosen ciphertext security of ElGamal we
我们需要一个更强的假设，哈希Diffie-Hellman
actually need a stronger assumption, Hash Diffie-Hellman or Computational Diffie-Hellman
或计算Diffie-Hellman假设不足以证明
这个系统的选择密文安全，就我们目前所知
are actually not enough to prove
chosen ciphertext security of the system as far
那么为了证明选择密文安全，我要引入一个新的假设
as we know. So to prove chosen-ciphertext
security, I'm going to introduce a new
叫做交互Diffie-Hellman假设。实际上
assumption called Interactive Diffie
Hellman assumption. And actually,
从技术上讲，我们真不喜欢这个假设。
稍后，我们将试图回避这一假设
technically we really don't like this
assumption. And we're going to try to get
但现在。我们只是想分析
rid of this, later on. But for now, we
just want to analyze the security of the
基本ElGamal系统对抗选择密文攻击的安全性。
basic ElGamal system against chosen
ciphertext attack. So to argue that it is
为了证明它是选择密文安全的，这是这个假设的内容
chosen ciphertext secure, here is what the
assumption says. Basically the challenger
开始时，挑战者和攻击者玩个游戏，他生成了一个随机的g
starts, you know, plays a game with the
adversary, he generates a random G,
生成两个指数，然后与往常一样，他给攻击者
generates two exponents, and then he says
to the adversary as usual, G, G to the a
g, g^a, g^b。现在攻击者的目标是解出
and G to the b. Now the adversary's goal
is basically to figure out the
Diffie-Hellman的密钥，即g^ab。
他输出v的值
Diffie-Helmman's secrets, mainly g to the
ab. He outputs the value of V and he wins
攻击者赢得这场游戏，如果v正好等于g^ab。
那么，目前为止这个假设
the game if V happens to be equal to G to
the AB. So, so far this looks identical to
和计算Diffie-Hellman假设看起来一样，没有区别
the Computational Diffie-Hellman assumption,
there's no difference - this is
这就是计算Diffie-Hellman假设，
但是在交互Diffie-Hellman假设中
the Computational Diffie-Hellman assumption
except in Interactive Diffie-Hellman would
会赋予攻击者稍微多一点的能力，那么因为攻击者能力更强
give the attacker a little bit more power.
So because the attacker has more power,
更难满足这个假设，这也是为什么我们说这个假设
it's harder to satisfy the assumption,
which is why we say that this assumption
比计算Diffie-Hellman还强。现在赋予的能力是什么？
is stronger than Computational
Diffie-Hellman. Now what is this power to be
进行询问的能力。特别地，攻击者可以提交
given? We are given the ability to make
queries. In particular, he gets to submit
群G中的两个元素，那么u1，v1是群G中的一对元素
two elements from the group G, so U1, V1
is a pair from the group G. And then he's
然后他被告知u1^a是否等于v1。
如果u1^a等于v1，他会得到1
told whether U1 to the A is equal to V1,
so he gets one, if U1 to the A equals
否则他会得到0。是个有点怪异的询问
to V1 and he gets zero, otherwise. It's kind of a
bizarre type of query. What, how does it
它能怎样帮助攻击者呢？但实际上我们可以给攻击者
be possibly help the attacker? But it
turns out we need to be able to answer
回答这类请求，为了能够证明选择密文安全性
these types of queries to the adversary in
order to be able to prove chosen
事实上攻击者可以一次次地进行这类询问
ciphertext security. And in fact, he can
do these type of queries again and again
那么他可以进行提交尽可能多的像这样的询问
and again. So he can issue as many
queries like these as he wants and then the
然后这个假设是说，尽管有所有这些询问
assumption says that despite all these
queries he still can't figure out the
攻击者依然无法解出Diffie-Hellman密钥，
就是说尽管做出了这么多的询问
Diffie-Hellman secret, namely despite
making all these queries, the probability
攻击者正确输出Diffie-Hellman密钥的概率依然是可忽略的
that he outputs the
Diffie-Hellman secret is negligible. Okay.
那么很明显如果这个假设成立，则计算
Diffie-Hellman假设也成立
So clearly if this assumption holds, that the Computational Diffie-Hellman assumption
因为这里的攻击者能力更强，因此我们说
holds, because here, the adversary has more power,
and as a result we say that this assumption
这个假设比计算Diffie-Hellman更强。
我们不喜欢这个假设的地方在于
is stronger that Computational Diffie-Hellman, the thing, we really don't like about this
实际上它是交互的，攻击者可以
assumption, is the fact, that, it's
interactive, and that the adversary is allowed to
向挑战者进行询问，如我所说，我们稍后
make queries to the challenger, and as I
said, we're gonna trying to get rid
将回避这种交互性。但是现在我告诉大家
of this interaction later on. But for now
I'll tell you that under this Interactive
在这个交互Diffie-Hellman假设下
Diffie-Hellman assumption and under the
assumption that the symmetric encryption
对称加密系统提供了认证加密，并且在这个假设下
system provides authenticated encryption, and
under the assumption that the hash
哈希函数是某个理想的哈希函数，我们叫做随机神谕
function is kind of an ideal hash
function, what we call the random oracle,
那么事实上ElGamal系统是选择密文安全的
then in fact the ElGamal system is chosen ciphertext secure and again this
这里的RO表示是在随机神谕的前提下
RO here denotes the fact that it's in the
random oracle model. Which is not
对我们的目标来说这并不重要。主要需要记住的是
important, so much for our purposes. The
main thing to remember that under
在这种奇怪的、交互的假设下，我们可以证明
kind of this weird, interactive
assumption we can actually prove that
ElGamal是选择密文安全的。到目前为止
ElGamal is a chosen ciphertext secure.
And as far as we know this assumption
我们知道这个假设对Z_p^*成立。那么接下来
actually holds for the group ZP star.
So what we're gonna do next is basically
我们回答这个问题：我们能否回避交互假设？
answer this question of whether we can get
rid of the interactive assumption. Can we
我们能否给出基于CDH的安全性证明？
类似地，我们的证明能否
prove security strictly based on CDH? And
similarly can we proof security without
不依赖于随机神谕？无需假设
relying on random oracles? Just you know
without having to assume, that the hash
哈希函数是理想的。我们能否使用具体的哈希函数
function is ideal. Just you know, can we
prove security using a concrete hash
完成安全性证明？我们下节简要讨论之
function. And we'll do that very briefly
in the next segment.